Finding Aid for Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory (University of Michigan) records, 1980-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory (University of Michigan) records 1980-1990
University of Michigan. Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory.
1 linear feet
0590 Bimu 2
The Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory (CSMIL) was established in 1985 as a joint venture with the School of Business, College of Engineering, and College of Literature, Science and the Arts. Gary Olson served as director from 1985 to 1994. Records detail the establishment of the laboratory and include committee minutes, financial records, announcements, and material on the colloquium series and various distinguished scientists invited to speak on artificial intelligence, spatial reasoning, and visualization of information.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donor No. 9576.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open without restriction.
The Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory (CSMIL) was established in 1985 as a joint venture with the School of Business, College of Engineering, and College of Literature, Science and the Arts. Gary Olson served as director from 1985 to 1994. In 1988 the Regents approved a project to build a Collaboration Technology Suite for the Laboratory in the Business School. The CSMIL eventually evolved into the Collaboratory for Research on Electronic Work (CREW).
The records consist of Topical Files, alphabetically arranged, which document various aspects of the Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory's administrative activities and research endeavors.
Within this series, Cognitive Science Course contains records pertaining courses which offered students a multidisciplinary approach to the study of cognition. These courses were proposed and offered between 1986 and 1988. Files contain correspondence, proposals, and course descriptions.
Colloquium Series contains programs, correspondence, and bulletins from colloquia sponsored and organized by the Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory.
The Newsletters series contains the CSMIL Bulletin, the main publication of the Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory, published biweekly. It provided a calendar of relevant events, colloquia, and workshops, as well as other announcements. Towards the late 1980s, the bulletin contained lengthier articles. This series also contains two editions of Express, a publication that updated the broader scientific community on the accomplishments of the EXPRES project, an electronic communication initiative.
Open Houses contains administrative documents, such as hand outs, to-do lists, and screen-shot print outs, relating to the CSMIL open houses.
Sloan Foundation contains records of the grant received to establish a program in Cognitive Science. The files include the final report to the Sloan Foundation on the project's development and activities.
Technical Reports include six spiral-bound versions of published reports co-authored by members of the Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory. The reports appeared in various journals, including Journal of Experimental Psychology, and the Journal on Expert Systems.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Cognitive Science and Machine Intelligence Laboratory.; Artificial intelligence.; Human-computer interaction--Study and teaching.; Interactive computer systems.; Olson, Gary M.
- Topical Files
  - Announcements, 1980-1985 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1982-1986 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Plan, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Background Materials, ca. 1985 (Box 1)
  - Behavioral Decision Training Course, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Brochures on Human Computer Interaction Programs, undated (Box 1)
  - Budget Summary Reports, 1986-1993 (Box 1)
  - Chinese Delegation, 1985
  - Cognitive Science Course (Box 1)
    - Course Proposal, undated (Box 1)
    - Planning Committee, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Teaching, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Colloquium Series
    - Colloquium Series, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Colloquium Series, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Commercialization Workshop, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Connection Machine, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Agendas, 1985-1987 (Box 1)
  - Flyers
  - Newsletters (Box 1)
    - CSMIL Bulletin, 1986 (Box 1)
    - CSMIL Bulletin, 1987 (Box 1)
    - CSMIL Bulletin, 1988 (Box 1)
    - CSMIL Bulletin, 1989 (Box 1)
    - CSMIL Bulletin, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Express (Box 1)
  - Open Houses
    - April 30, 1987 (Box 1)
    - October 11, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Posters (Box 1)
  - Program Description, 1988 undated (Box 1)
  - Progress Reports, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Report on Activities, Budget, Administration, 1985-1986
  - Sloan Foundation (Box 1)
    - Sloan Foundation, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Sloan Foundation Final Report, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Technical Reports
    - "Structure and Process in Semantic Memory", April, 1987 (Box 1)
    - "A Qualitative Approach for Recovering Relative Depths in Dynamic Scenes", June, 1987 (Box 1)
    - "Mental Models in Human-Computer Interaction", June, 1987 (Box 1)
    - "Extracting Expertise from Experts", June, 1987 (Box 1)
    - "An Advantage Model of Choice", September, 1987 (Box 1)
    - "Can Principles of Cognition Lower the Barriers to Programming?", September, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Vision Workshop (Box 1)